Guide to the Yale Rockefeller Theatrical Prints Collection
Yale University Arts Library
Yale Rockefeller theatrical prints collection
1934-1976
DRA 9
Yale University Arts Library
128.75
(103 boxes)
The collection comprises photographic prints and reproductions of theatres, costumes, scenes, companies, masks, properties, and portraits documenting the classical stage to the mid-twentieth century from around the world.
Nicoll, Allardyce, 1894-1976
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Rockefeller Collection was housed in the Yale School of Drama Library until its transfer to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library in 2008.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Biographical / Historical
The Yale Rockefeller Theatrical Prints Collection was created in the 1930s under the guidance of Allardyce Nicoll, then chair of the Department of Drama in the School of Fine Arts. Funded by the Rockefeller Foundation, graduate students in Drama accompanied Nicoll to Europe and generated thousands of photographic prints from libraries, museums, and private collections relating to all aspects of theatre history. The collection was supplemented by visual material collected from all over the world.
Scope and Contents
The collection comprises photographic prints and reproductions of theatres, costumes, scenes, companies, masks, properties, and portraits documenting the classical stage to the mid-twentieth century from around the world. The collection also contains journals recording the origin of the photographic prints by print number.
Arrangement
Organized into three series: I. Card Files. II. Prints. III. Miscellaneous.
The card files and prints are arranged sequentially by print classification and number. For example, "D.D.1.#" corresponds to "Costumes, 16th Century, Italy, Print number."
A guide to the original classification system is provided below:
TOPIC
A Theatres
B Scenes
C Groups (stage groupings)
D Costumes
E Masks
F Properties
G Machines
H Lighting
I Audience (people or auditoria)
J Dances (most ballet under D)
K Portraits (non-theatrical)
L Fairs
M Commedia
MA Pantomimes
N Pageants & Processions
O Marionettes
P Circus
Q Makeup
R Film
S Misc (including non-theatrical costume)
T Ceremonials
DATE
A Greek
B Roman
C Medieval
D 16th Century
E 1600-1650
F 1650-1700
G 1700-1750
H 1750-1800
I 1800-1850
J 1850-1900
K 1900-1914
L 1914-1934
M 1935-
ORIGIN
1 Italy
2 France
3 England
4 Spain
5 Germany
6 United States
7 Austria
8 Russia
9 Poland
10 Sweden
11 Norway
12 Denmark
13 Holland
14 Belgium
15 Switzerland
16 Finland
17 Czechoslovakia
18 Greece
19 Hungary
20 China
21 Japan
22 India
23 Byzantine
24 Turkey
25 Java
26 Mexico and Central America
27 Canada
28 Africa
Theater -- History; Photographic prints; Nagler, A. M. (Alois Maria), 1907-1993
- Card Files, Series I; 22
  Arrangement
  Arranged sequentially by print classification and number. Four card boxes (A-D) per Paige box.
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the former card files, which cataloged and indexed the print collection.
  - Theatres – Scenes (Box 1)
    - Theatres A.120.1 – A.G.1.58.1, 1A
    - Theatres A.G.1.60 – A.J.36.1, 1B
    - Theatres A.K.1.1.4 – Scenes B.F.1.426, 1C
    - Scenes B.F.1.500 – Scenes B.G.1.5000, 1D
  - Scenes – Scenes (Box 2)
    - Scenes B.G.1.6000 – Scenes B.I.1.702, 2A
    - Scenes B.I.1.800 – Scenes B.J.7.94, 2B
    - Scenes B.J.7.10 – Scenes B.L.6.1706, 2C
    - Scenes B.L.6.1801 – Scenes B.M.6.173, 2D
  - Scenes – Costumes (Box 3)
    - Scenes B.M.6.1901 – Costumes D.C.14.220-223, 3A
    - Costumes D.D.1.1 – Costumes D.D.13.1, 3B
    - Costumes D.E.1.1 – Costumes D.F.2.694.13, 3C
    - Costumes D.F.2.694.14 – Costumes D.H.2.415, 3D
  - Costumes – Costumes (Box 4)
    - Costumes D.H.2.418 – Costumes D.H.3.25.000, 4A
    - Costumes D.H.5.100 – Costumes D.I.3.360, 4B
    - Costumes D.I.3.400 – Costumes D.I.5.2623, 4C
    - Costumes D.I. 5.2624 – Costumes D.J.6.750, 4D
  - Costumes – Commedia (Box 5)
    - Costumes D.J.6.751 – Costumes D.K.2.3026, 5A
    - Costumes D.K.3.1 – Costumes D.M.6.306, 5B
    - Costumes D.M.6.311 – Portraits K.J.6.172, 5C
    - Portraits K.J.6.173 – Commedia M.d.d.2, 5D
  - Commedia – Angus W. (Box 6)
    - Commedia M.e.400 – Pageants N.G.14.36, 6A
    - Pageants N.H.1.2—Miscellaneous S.E.1.602, 6B
    - Miscellaneous S.E.1.700 – Miscellaneous S.M.6.11, 6C
    - Aabel, H. – Angus W., 6D
  - Animals – Briseis (Box 7)
    - Animals – At the Gate of the Kingdom, 7A
    - Atellanas – Barry, Eleanor, 7B
    - Barry, Elizabeth – Bibico, 7C
    - Bibiena – Briseis, 7D
  - Bristol, England – Chronology: 1809 (Box 8)
    - Bristol, England – Casting a Boomerang, 8A
    - Castle – Chronology: 1599, 8B
    - Chronology:1600 – Chronology: 1729, 8C
    - Chronology: 1730 – Chronology: 1809, 8D
  - Chronology: 1810 – Costumes (Box 9)
    - Chronology: 1810 – Chronology: 1900, 9A
    - Chronology: 1889 – Clowns, 9B
    - Cloyd Head – Costume Ball, 9C
    - Costumes – Costumes, 9D
  - Costumes – Costumes (Box 10)
    - Costumes – Costumes, 10A
    - Costumes – Costumes, 10B
    - Costumes – Costumes, 10C
    - Costumes – Costumes, 10D
  - Costumes – Costumes (Box 11)
    - Costumes – Costumes, 11A
    - Costumes – Costumes, 11B
    - Costumes – Costumes, 11C
    - Costumes – Costumes, 11D
  - Costumes – Costumes (Box 12)
    - Costumes – Costumes, 12A
    - Costumes – Costumes, 12B
    - Costumes – Costumes, 12C
    - Costumes – Costumes, 12D
  - Costumes – Father Time (Box 13)
    - Costumes – Cziossek, Felix, 13A
    - Dabadie, Marie – Diomede, 13B
    - Dionysiac Mysteries – Edwards, Charlie, 13C
    - Edwin, John – Father Time, 13D
  - Fatima – Haun (Box 14)
    - Fatima – Flore, Mlle., 14A
    - Genlis, Marquis de Pisy – Florence, 14B
    - Genoa – Greek, 14C
    - Green, Adolph – Haun, 14D
  - Hauptmann, Gerhart – Lissardo (Box 15)
    - Hauptmann, Gerhart – Hyria, 15A
    - I Am Guilty – Jones, H.A., 15B
    - Jones, Inigo – Kyse, Frantisek, 15C
    - Labarre, T. – Lissardo, 15D
  - Liston, John – Mimes (Box 16)
    - Liston, John – Luce, Clair, 16A
    - Lucerne – Les Maries, 16B
    - Mariet, Jean – Mason, W., 16C
    - Masque Gaiety – Mimes, 16D
  - Minaggio – Palie (Box 17)
    - Minaggio – Munkenwendt, 17A
    - Mural – Nysa, 17B
    - O., A – Palmer, Robert, 17C
    - Palmira – Palie, 17D
  - Patara – Rehan, P. (Box 18)
    - Patara – Plastic Sets, 18A
    - Platea – Properties, 18B
    - Properties – Properties, 18C
    - Properties – Rehan, P., 18D
  - Rehburg, Hans – Scenes (Box 19)
    - Rehburg, Hans – Room, 19A
    - Roos, J. – Scelin, 19B
    - Scena – Scenes, 19C
    - Scenes – Scenes, 19D
  - Scenes – Shakespeare: Love's Labors Lost (Box 20)
    - Scenes – Scenes, 20A
    - Scenes – Scenes, 20B
    - Scenes – Schildkraut, 20C
    - Schiller – Shakespeare: Love's Labors Lost, 20D
  - Shakespeare: Macbeth – Theatre (Box 21)
    - Shakespeare: Macbeth – Sims, G., 21A
    - Simultaneous Set – Strophilus, 21B
    - Stroppa, Pietro – Thatchwork, 21C
    - Theatres – Theatre, 21D
  - Theatres – Zwölf Mädchen (Box 22)
    - Theatres – Townsend, F.H., 22A
    - Townsman – Vasconus, Philippus, 22B
    - Vase – Weber, 22C
    - Weblings – Zwölf Mädchen, 22D
- Prints, Series II; 67 boxes
  This series contains the corresponding photographic prints referenced in the card files.
  Arranged sequentially by print classification and number.
  - THEATRES, A.24.1 – A.D.1990.1 (Box 23)
  - THEATRES, A.D.1.1998 – A.E.1.4000.47 (Box 24)
  - THEATRES, A.E.2.50 – A.G.1.21 (Box 25)
  - THEATRES, A.G.1.40 – A.H.2.703 (Box 26)
  - THEATRES, A.H.2.800 – A.J.3.5 (Box 27)
  - THEATRES, A.J.3.10 – A.L.3.5.102.2 (Box 28)
  - THEATRES – SCENES, A.L.5.1 – B.3.1.821.17 (Box 29)
  - SCENES, B.E.1.822 – B.E.3.283 (Box 30)
  - SCENES, B.E.3.300 – B.F.1.822.47 (Box 31)
  - SCENES, B.F.2.719 – B.G.1.340 (Box 32)
  - SCENES, B.F.2.719 – B.G.1.340 (Box 33)
  - SCENES, B.G.1.350 – B.G.1.15.000 (Box 34)
  - SCENES, B.G.2.85 – B.H.1.55 (Box 35)
  - SCENES, B.H.I.100 – B.H.7.15 (Box 36)
  - SCENES, B.H.7.25 – B.I.1.666 (Box 37)
  - SCENES, B.I.1.800 – B.I.3.632 (Box 38)
  - SCENES, B.I.5.1 – B.J.3.1302 (Box 39)
  - SCENES, B.J.3.1303 – B.K.5.1 (Box 40)
  - SCENES, B.K.5.2 – B.L.5.1443 (Box 41)
  - SCENES, B.L.5.1475 – B.L.7.748 (Box 42)
  - SCENES, B.L.7.749 – B.M.5.140 (Box 43)
  - SCENES – GROUPS, B.M.5.147 – C.G.71 (Box 44)
  - GROUPS, C.H.1.1 – C.J.6.2401 (Box 45)
  - GROUPS – COSTUMES, C.J.6.2402-D.C.5.3565 (Box 46)
  - COSTUMES, D.C.7.1050 – D.D.1.3191.73 (Box 47)
  - COSTUMES, D.D.1.3192 – D.D.1.3599 (Box 48)
  - COSTUMES, D.D.1.3600 – D.E.3.177 (Box 49)
  - COSTUMES, D.E.3.183 – D.F.1.1112 (Box 50)
  - COSTUMES, D.F.1.113 – D.F.1.1389 (Box 51)
  - COSTUMES, D.F.1.1390 – D.F.2.692.13 (Box 52)
  - COSTUMES, D.F.2.693 – D.F.2.8241 (Box 53)
  - COSTUMES, D.F.2.8242 – D.F.2.8653 (Box 54)
  - COSTUMES, D.F.2.8654 – D.G.2.327 (Box 55)
  - COSTUMES, D.G.2.400 – D.H.2.163.2 (Box 56)
  - COSTUMES, D.H.2.164 – D.H.2.2508 (Box 57)
  - COSTUMES, D.H.2.2509 – D.H.3.7602 (Box 58)
  - COSTUMES, D.H.3.7604 – D.H.7.3 (Box 59)
  - COSTUMES, D.H.7.4 – D.I.2.1275 (Box 60)
  - COSTUMES, D.I.2.1276 – D.I.2.12017 (Box 61)
  - COSTUMES, D.I.2.12019 – D.I.3.11513 (Box 62)
  - COSTUMES, D.I.3.12001 – D.I.5.454 (Box 63)
  - COSTUMES, D.I.5.500 – D.I.7.278 (Box 64)
  - COSTUMES, D.I.7.300 – D.J.6.53 (Box 65)
  - COSTUMES, D.J.3.100 – D.J.6.53 (Box 66)
  - COSTUMES, D.J.6.60 – D.J.6.2514 (Box 67)
  - COSTUMES, D.J.6.2515 – D.J.7.104 (Box 68)
  - COSTUMES, D.J.7.150 – D.J.10.10009 (Box 69)
  - COSTUMES, D.J.10.10,010.1 – D.K.11.263 (Box 70)
  - COSTUMES, D.K.11.282 – D.L.8.26 (Box 71)
  - COSTUMES, D.L.8.200 – D.M.31.1 (Box 72)
  - MASKS – PROPERTIES – MACHINES – LIGHTING – AUDIENCE – DANCES, E.A.18.2 – J.H.7.109 (Box 73)
  - DANCES – PORTRAITS, J.H.7.1221 – K.I.6.13 (Box 74)
  - PORTRAITS, K.J.101 – K.J.6.177 (Box 75)
  - PORTRAITS – FAIRS – PANTOMIMES, K.J.6.178 – Ma 258 (Box 76)
  - PANTOMIMES – COMMEDIA, Ma209 – Md 400.1 (Box 77)
  - COMMEDIA, M.d.1604 – M.s.820 (Box 78)
  - COMMEDIA – PAGEANTS & PROCESSIONS, M.s.821 – N.D.2.25 (Box 79)
  - PAGEANTS & PROCESSIONS, N.D.2.3 – N.E.1.856 (Box 80)
  - PAGEANTS & PROCESSIONS, N.E.1.857 – N.F.1.500.102 (Box 81)
  - PAGEANTS & PROCESSIONS, N.F.1.503 – N.H.1.309 (Box 82)
  - PAGEANTS & PROCESSIONS – MARIONETTES – CIRCUS – MAKE-UP – MISC., N.H.2.10 – S.D.1.399 (Box 83)
  - MISC., S.D.1.400 – S.E.2.51 (Box 84)
  - MISC., S.E.2.10 – S.G.3.604 (Box 85)
  - MISC., S.G.3.625 – S.I.3.1253 (Box 86)
  - MISC., S.I.3.1254 – S.M.6.6 (Box 87)
  - THEATRES – PAGEANTS & PROCESSIONS, OVERSIZE (Box 88)
  - MISC., OVERSIZE (Box 89)
- Miscellaneous, Series III
  This series contains additional materials, including notes, records, and prints from the files of A.M. (Alois Maria) Nagler, who joined the faculty at Yale in 1946 and taught theater history until he retired from the Yale School of Drama in 1976.
  - RECORDS: NEGATIVES, PRINTS, PHOTOGRAPHS (Box 90, Folder 1-7)
  - RECORDS: NEGATIVES, PRINTS, PHOTOGRAPHS (Box 91, Folder 8-14)
  - RECORDS: NEGATIVES, PRINTS, PHOTOGRAPHS (Box 92, Folder 15-20)
  - UNIDENTIFIED PRINTS FROM THE FILES OF A.M. NAGLER (Box 93)
  - UNIDENTIFIED PRINTS FROM THE FILES OF A.M. NAGLER (Box 94)
  - UNIDENTIFIED PRINTS FROM THE FILES OF A.M. NAGLER (Box 95)
  - UNIDENTIFIED PRINTS FROM THE FILES OF A.M. NAGLER (Box 96)
  - UNIDENTIFIED PRINTS FROM THE FILES OF A.M. NAGLER (Box 97)
  - UNIDENTIFIED PRINTS FROM THE FILES OF A.M. NAGLER (Box 98)
  - UNIDENTIFIED PRINTS FROM THE FILES OF A.M. NAGLER (Box 99)
  - UNIDENTIFIED PRINTS FROM THE FILES OF A.M. NAGLER (Box 100)
  - UNIDENTIFIED PRINTS FROM THE FILES OF A.M. NAGLER (Box 101)
  - UNIDENTIFIED PRINTS FROM THE FILES OF A.M. NAGLER (Box 102)
  - The Yale – Rockefeller Theatre Collection Notes for Cataloguers and Records, 2 (Box 103)
    The box contains a binder with typescript notes prepared by Allardyce Nicoll in 1937 regarding "the scope of the collection and the methods employed in filing, cataloguing and cross indexing." It also contains a records notebook, otherwise referred to as a "diary," which was used to record the roll number of the film, shot list, and source material.